What is your view on where things, where we are right now, especially with Fintechs and
the role that's crypto is playing in the future of finance?
I think the fundamentals have to change, particularly with autonomous banking and finance that's
coming.
We're seeing sort of net new infrastructure emerge on that front, but already today, Fintechs
are really dominant and globally. The top 20 retail Fintechs in the world have amassed
about 4.1 billion customers over the last 10 years. Comparatively, the top 20 retail
banks in the world have only 2.7 billion customers. All of the growth, of course, is
coming in the Fintech arena. Digital onboarding and digital acquisition of customers, digital
acquisition of deposits, this is all really reshaping the economics in the way we think
about banking as a disruption.
You're right, from digital onboarding and everything digital first, obviously has changed
a lot. The idea of a bank branch is, hopefully soon will disappear forever. What do we double
click on, the role that you see crypto in particular, or stablecoins play in the future of banking?
How do you see that ecosystem play out of the interaction of banking and digital assets?
We've just seen recently, the stablecoins have surpassed MasterCard and Visa's card
volume for transactions globally. If we're starting to talk about smart contract development,
this is really the foundational element of how we think about autonomous finance operating
in the future. This requires net new infrastructure. The old fiat currencies, the old cool banking
systems, these really amplify the purpose for the type of autonomous banking and finance
that we need to build, to build the smart economies of the future. This is the foundational element
of what's coming next.
Actually, I want to focus on this autonomous banking you mentioned with the smart contracts
and crypto playing a pivotal role in it. What impact do you think it will have on the current
financial system? If and when we have the rise of autonomous banking, as you call it?
There's going to be a huge amount of effort in traditional banking to try and interface
with smart contracting. We see, obviously, players like Jake and me but others creating
their own points. We see a circle of MasterCard's partnership, etc. There's a lot of effort
right now to sort of create a bridge between those two systems. But the reality is, what
we have historically called decentralized finance, DeFi, is what TradFi will essentially have
to become relevant for autonomous finance. When I talk about autonomous finance, I'm
talking about the autonomous operation of banking and finance that supports all of the AI-driven
and gigantic driven systems that we need. Whether that's supply chain automation, whether
it's dark factories or autonomous factories, whether it's drones delivering packages or
yourself driving car, delivering you to your destination. These are all components of this
autonomous world that we're building and we need fit for purpose finance and banking
that is capable of existing in that world. You can't have batch-based payment systems
and that type of legacy infrastructure running this real-time autonomous capabilities. That's
why we look around the world today. Even when it comes to payments, all of the fastest-growing
payments networks, real-time payments networks, kicks in Brazil, UPI layer in India, the mobile
commerce layer in China, etc. This is essentially this net new infrastructure that's capable
of real-time gigantic AI-based payments.
What this infrastructure talking about, Brett, do you even believe the legacy financial system
can even transform itself? Obviously, you've been talking about the impact of FinTech on
the future of banking for a decade now. I still get my bank asked me to go in person
or they were asking for wet signatures, that's for proof of addresses. We may have overestimated
the capabilities for many banks to adapt to the new reality. Do you believe that a new
banking system could involve the old players changing or be basically completely some of
the new players coming in, either FinTech's crypto firms and basically completely taking
over the legacy banks?
That's really reshaping the way we think of what is a bank. Today, if you look at the
top 50 fastest-growing financial institutions in the world, there's not one traditional
player amongst them. You've got to translate that to market share shift. Ten years ago,
we would say, well, these FinTech players, they're not yet profitable. They're only
growing so rapidly because they're small or they can't manage risk as good as the traditional
players, but all of that's false because now we've seen that sort of play out. What's left
is the big bank sort of their only defense right now. Yes, but they don't have the asset
size of the big players. My question is to bank boards and executives today is, how is
your asset size going to help you become an AI-relevant bank for this what's coming the
next generation? That is sort of, I think, the key problem. You need technical and cultural
agility to be able to make that transformation. There's certainly less than 10% of the banks
in the world that we see, traditional large players, who are going to be able to make
that leap because it's just a different approach and different components.
In breadth, we have 30 seconds left, but you mentioned that 10% of banks have the agility
to be able to transition. There's a lot of people that work in finance. Many bankers
listening to the show, as a futurist, if there's one piece of advice you have for people working
in finance, listening to the show, knowing what you know about what the future of finance
may look like, what's your advice to them?
So I always get asked, I'm sure you do. Who's the best bank in the world that we should
copy who does this really well? Is it JP Morgan or DBS? You're asking the wrong question.
To survive this transition, you have to be a technology company. So look at New Bank,
look at We Bank, look at Antworth. That is the template for what you need to become.
And that requires you to forget everything you knew about banking in the past and become
the digital first organization.
I love it. Thank you very much. That was author of Futurist, Brett King. Brett, thanks
for joining us today. Very interesting in what's happening in the future of finance.